

O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

About Me

I' m a seasoned professional with a solid 25-year career in the Oil&Gas Industry, where I have held roles of increasing responsibility in Operations, Projects and Engineering.

My passion for technology led me to acquire strong IT skills, particularly in backend development. With expertise in Java, databases, and proficency in DevOps and AWS, I am well-bersed in agile methodologies and CRM software like Salesforce.

I am excited to explore new opportunities in the field of information technology or project management, where I can contribute to the development of creative and efficient solutions.

Contact Me

- gjlobos141@gmail.com
- +5493489593664
- Campana, Buenos Aires Argentina
- in linkedin.com/in/gjlobos/?locale=en_US
- github.com/gjlobos
- https://www.salesforce.com/trailblazer/gilobos

Oil&Gas Hard Skills

- Distribution Terminals Operation, Maintenance and Design.
- Atmospheric and pressurized tanks Operation
- Docks Operation, Maintenance and Design.
- Management of Change (MOC)
- Process Safety and Risk management (PSM -IRM) - Product Hazard - Aviation Fuels
- Fire Emergency Response system (NFPA)
- Project Management (MS-Project | PM4R Agile)
- Production and Inventory Accounting VMPA
- ISO Internal Auditor (9001 14001)
- Measurements standards (API MPMS)

Languages

Spanish Native

English Full professional proficiency

French Elementary proficiency

Soft Skills

- Teamwork player | Active-listener
- Leadership Empathy and Member Support
- Attention to Details Problem Solver
- Creativity and Innovation
- Excellent Communication (Oral and Written)
- Continuous Learning Flexibility / Adaptability
- Agile Methodologies (Scrum Kanban)

IT Hard Skills

- Backend developer | Java NodeJS Spring
 Boot API Rest Maven Hibernate Microservices Go
- Frontend developer | JS React HTML CSS
- Database | MySQL Workbench MongoDB -PostgreSQL
- Testing | Manual Automated Postman Junit
 RestAssured Selenium
- Infraestructure | AWS (VPC, EC2, S3, RDS)
- DevOps | Linux Terraform Docker K8S
- Github | Gitlab | Trello | Jira | Confluence | MS-Project | Slack | Discord | Notion
- Salesforce SAP
- Power-BI / Excel dashboards and data analysis



O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

Education

 Full Stack Developer (Backend Specialist) (Jun-2021 to Jun-2023)

Digital House

- Master in Business Administration (2001)
 Instituto Desarrollo Económico Argentino (IDEA)
- Electronics Engineering (1988 1995)
 Instituto Tecnológico de Buenos Aires (ITBA)

Courses & Certifications

 Event "Transforming Project Management: the role of AI" (May-2024)

DoInGlobal

- Agile Explorer (May-2024)
 IBM
- Explore Emerging Tech (May-2024)
 IBM
- PM4R Agile Innovation Projects (Jun-2023)
 DoInGlobal BID

Agile & Innovation Project Management

• Salesforce Admin (Apr-2023)

Silvertech - Tribo

Trailhead virtual bootcamp for new Admins

• School of Devops (Nov-2022)

Endava

Devops training

Linux, Docker, Scripting, Cloud Vendors, IaC, K8S

 Getting Started with AWS CloudFormation (Sep-2022)

AWS

 Excel: Create an intuitive and impactful dashboard from scratch (Jul-2020)

Linkedin

- Excel: Data Analysis (Jul-2020)
 Linkedin
- Excel: Enter data correctly (Jun-2020)
 Linkedin
- Excel: Pivot tables (Jun-2020)
 Linkedin
- Petroleum Measurements (2015)
 University of Texas Petroleum Extension Service

<u>Professional Experience</u>

Backend Developer - Digital Wallet Project Digital House

May 2023 - June 2023

Key responsibilities:

- Backend development using API Rest for a Digital Wallet Microservices Application
- Language: Java with SpringBoot
- Use of Keycloak for authorization and authentication (IAM)
- API documentation with Swagger
- Exceptions and Logging
- Relational database design (MySQL, Workbench)
- Manual and Automated Testing (Postman, JUnit, RestAssured)
- Infraestructure deploy with AWS services (EC2, S3, VPC)
- Shell scripting, Virtual Machines, Terraform, Docker, Kubernetes

Full Stack Developer - DigiRent Project Digital House

May 2022 - June 2022

- Front-end development for a Rental Properties
 Web Application
- Web page design (FIGMA, responsive, accesibility)
- APIs integration (front-end and back-end)
- Back-end development (JAVA, Spring Boot, Maven)
- Entities, services, controllers, endpoints
- Exceptions and Logging (Log4J)
- Relational database design (MySQL, Workbench)
- Logical models (DER), entities, attributes, joins, queries.
- Manual and Automated Testing (Postman, Jest, Selenium)
- AWS services (EC2, S3, RDS, VPC)
- Shell scripting, Virtual Machines, Terraform, Docker



O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

Work Experience

Downstream Oil&Gas Technical Consultant

April 2021 - April 2022

Key responsibilities:

- Hydrocarbon Measurement Systems Audits
- Oil Loss Analysis and Audits
- Measurement Practices Training
- Measurement Software Projects

Head of Process Engineering Oil Movement and Storage, Docks, LPG, Coke and Water Treatment plant (Campana Refinery -Axionenergy)

Feb 2018 - Sept 2020

Key responsibilities:

- Leader of Process Design Specifications and Operations support team. International standards compliance (API, NFPA, ASTM, ANSI).
- Technical guidance to solve operational facilities issues.
- Team responsible for Management of Change (MOC) development of technical issues, authorizations management and tracking.
- Risk analysis technical member (Process Safety, Risk Assessments, Hazop, LOPA, MOC) related to every equipment or facility incharged, define probability and consequence of scenario and set action plans and priorities. Follow-up.
- Preparation of business cases for CAPEX projects.
 Follow up of project stages and collaboration with project and operations team.
- Monitoring and design of key facilities EHS indicators to avoid incidents (alarms, operational and design limits).
- Project management related to new technologies (instrumentation & software).
- Hydrocarbon Measurement and Oil Loss Specialist.
- Solution implementation for production accounting, balance, and data reconciliation applications (VMPA - KBC)

Inventory Control and Measurements Specialist (Campana Refinery-Axionenergy)

July 2014 - Feb 2018

Key responsibilities:

- Movements and Storage Oil Loss Management System coordinator.
- Responsible for the end-of-month closing process of the Refinery (closing of Inventories, control of tank measurements, reconciliation of dispatches and receptions, loss analysis, mass balance of the Refinery, improvement plans)
- Oil Loss Process analysis: continuous improvement, efficiency between functions, improvement of operational processes to reduce losses, automation to reduce uncertainties.
- Area contact point for internal and external measurement and control audits. Follow-up of pending items and recommendations.
- Development of material and delivery of training and certification courses for operators in tank measurement practices and volumetric meters.

Oil and Movements Project Coordinator (Campana Refinery - Axionenergy)

Jan 2011 - July 2014

- Contact of the area for the management of CAPEX projects. Work together with the project group and the area for preparation and compliance with the annual Capital Investment plan.
- Management of CAPEX projects and OPEX budget of items related to measurements and continuous improvement of the facilities.
- Refinery's local contact of Exxonmobil's global Controls System (HCP: Hydrocarbon Control Practices) that defines requirements for custody transfer measurements, inventories, internal consumption.
- Refinery's local contact of Exxonmobil's global Offsite network (Oil Spill best practices).
- Responsible for coordinating the end-of-month closing process of the Refinery (closing of Inventories, reconciliation of shipments and receipts, loss analysis, improvement plans).

O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

Work Experience (next)

Key responsibilities (next):

 Area contact point for internal and external measurement and control audits. Follow-up of pending items and recommendations.

Bussiness Unit Head (Docks, LPG, Effluent Treatment Plant, Coke pile and truck loading) (Campana Refinery - Exxonmobil)

Feb 2009 - Jan 2011

Key responsibilities:

- Area Manager for dispatch facilities at the Refinery: Docks, LPG storage and dispatch plant, effluent treatment plant, coke storage and dispatch, solvent storage and dispatch.
- Direct responsibility for the medium and long-term management of the facilities, operations support for short-term problem solving, OPEX/CAPEX plan management, compliance with laws and regulations (National Authorities), area's Safety, Health and Environment management system.
- Review and preparation of operating procedures, PDS of changes and modifications, monitoring of the annual and preventive maintenance plan (Interface with Maintenance).
- Ownership of Management of Change (MOC)
 process system related to the facilities incharged,
 authorizations management and tracking.
- Risk analysis member as owner of the facilities
 (Process Safety, Risk Assessments, Hazop, LOPA,
 MOC) related to every equipment or facility
 incharged, define probability and consequence of
 scenario and set action plans and priorities. Follow up.
- Ownership over the facilities management of the corporate program of safety, health, environment and security (ExxonMobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems - OIMS), process safety and personal safety improvements plans, incidents analysis and recommendations.
- Ownership of the Fire Emergency and Protection plans.

Oil & Movements Bussiness Unit Head Assistant (Campana Refinery -Exxonmobil)

July 2007 - Feb 2009

Key responsibilities:

- Assistance to the Head of Movement and Storage Area on issues related to the area: medium and long-term management of the facilities (tanks, pumps, piping), operations support for short-term problem solving, OPEX plan management /CAPEX, compliance with the Resol tank plan. 785, Safety, Hygiene and Environment management of the area.
- Review and preparation of operating procedures, PDS of changes and modifications, monitoring of the annual and preventive maintenance plan (Interface with Maintenance).
- Preparation of forms of Management of Change (MOC) process system related to the facilities of the area and tracking.
- Tracking of recommendations of ExxonMobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems -OIMS
- Quality management system procedures compliance and follow-up.
- Aviation Fuels JIG standards compliance Audits

Operational Supervisor (San Lorenzo Distribution Terminal - Exxonmobil)

June 2005 - July 2007

- Responsible for the operations and maintenance coordination and execution of the Terminal.
- Operations: ships unloading, atmospheric tanks operations, trucks loading and unloading, laboratory tests.
- Facilities: Dock, atmospheric tanks, loading rack, unloading rack, laboratory, pumps, pipelines.
- Leadership of maintenance and operations teams (10 own-people and 20 contractors).
- Exxonmobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems (OIMS) procedures follow-up.



O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

Work Experience (next)

Key responsibilities (next):

- Fire Emergency Response procedures follow-up.
- Process and Personal Safety, Health and Environment incident mitigation and investigation
- Coordination of Maintenance preventive and corrective plans execution.
- CAPEX projects coordination and annual plan follow-up.
- Preparation of forms of Management of Change (MOC) process system related to the facilities of the area and tracking.
- Quality management system procedures compliance and follow-up.

Operational Coordinator (San Lorenzo Distribution Terminal - Exxonmobil)

July 2003 - June 2005

Key responsibilities:

- Responsible for the operations coordination and execution of the Terminal.
- Operations: ships unloading, atmospheric tanks operations, trucks loading and unloading, laboratory tests.
- Facilities: Dock, atmospheric tanks, loading rack, unloading rack, laboratory.
- Leadership of operations teams (6 own-people).
- Exxonmobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems (OIMS) procedures follow-up.
- Fire Emergency Response procedures follow-up.
- Process and Personal Safety, Health and Environment incident mitigation and investigation.
- Preparation of forms of Management of Change (MOC) process system related to the facilities of the area and tracking.
- Quality management system procedures compliance and follow-up.

Maintenance Coordinator (San Lorenzo Distribution Terminal - Exxonmobil)

Sept 1998 - July 2003

Key responsibilities:

- Responsible for the maintenance coordination and execution of the Terminal.
- Operations: ships unloading, atmospheric tanks operations, trucks loading and unloading, laboratory tests.
- Facilities: Dock, atmospheric tanks, loading rack, unloading rack, laboratory, pumps, pipelines.
- Leadership of maintenance and operations teams (10 own-people and 20 contractors).
- Exxonmobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems (OIMS) procedures follow-up.
- Fire Emergency Response procedures follow-up.
- Process and Personal Safety, Health and Environment incident mitigation and investigation.
- Coordination of Maintenance preventive and corrective plans execution.
- CAPEX projects coordination and annual plan follow-up.
- Preparation of forms of Management of Change (MOC) process system related to the facilities of the area and tracking.

Truck Delivery Supervisor (Campana Distribution Terminal - Exxonmobil)

Aug 1995 - Sept 1998

- Supervision of the operations at the Terminal.
- Operations: trucks loading and unloading, quick laboratory tests, additives unloading.
- Facilities: loading rack, unloading rack, additives atmospheric tanks, filters.
- Supervision of drivers during loading and unloading.
- Exxonmobil's Operations Integrity Management Systems (OIMS) procedures follow-up.
- Fire Emergency Response procedures follow-up.
- Process and Personal Safety, Health and Environment incident mitigation and investigation.

O&G Downstream Engineer | Java Developer | Projects | Salesforce

Work Experience (next)

Key responsibilities (next):

- Preparation of forms of Management of Change (MOC) process system related to the facilities of the area and tracking.
- Quality management system procedures compliance and follow-up.

IT Helpdesk support ITS (onsite third party service in ESSO)

1994 - 1995

- Software installations (DOS, Windows, custom apps)
- Internal users support Software troubleshooting
- Internal users support Hardware troubleshooting